we will come you guys let's start discussing about the data link layer. So in the network
layer we know our tag will be like this. So this is the data and the TCP or UDP that will
be added and the port number will be added here and the source IP and the destination
IP will be added with our data it will be joined with our data. And in network layer
the main purpose of the network layer there is a one word like media access control
MAC address. So what is MAC address? So MAC address is unique address for every machine
inside your network. So that will not be changed it will be it will be persistent so the
MAC address will not be changed but if you see the IP address. So my IP address today
my IP address was let I will explain that I will show the what is my IP first. Here you
can find this is my IP address 18.29. But yesterday or day before yesterday my IP address
will be 18.27 the IP address was changed. So but if you see the MAC address so this is my
physical address it's my MAC address. So the MAC address will not be changed for any other
machines so it will be unique address for every machine. So we can easily track the data
inside the network. Okay let's take an example. So this is your router and here we can find
lot of machine. So our machine here. So today the IP address was 2 and 3, 4. So the MAC
address of the A0 is okay the MAC address will be like this way okay. So this is a unique
address physical address that was provided by the network interface card. This is the
network interface card. So if you are using the laptop the network interface card will
be like this inside your laptop. So how do I how do I think okay. So let's jump on to there
and it will be the address will be like this okay. So 94 dBC9 okay. So let's draw something
B0 and Z0 okay. So each machine have a unique I unique address. So I just we are sending
the packet today and the packet was receiving to Google servers okay. So in the data link
layer the main purpose was MAC address will be added with our data. So the source MAC and
the destination MAC. So both things will be added with our packet okay. So let's continue
our discussion. So today we are sending and receiving the data. So the next day so in the
first computers the IP was changed to 18.27. In the second computers the IP was changed to
18.68. And the third computers the it was changed to 18.57. So now so you can't
able to track the machine which machines send which packets okay. So if you are doing some
criminal activity in from the organization or from your network but in your network there
are 100 plus devices as they are if you are doing some criminal activity. So your cyber
time officers are police they are tracking. So who is doing that okay. So now if they
are searching with the specific IP address your private IP. So they can't able to find who
is the exact victim right. So the IP address will be changed okay. So if you go to the
control panel inside your network and in the network sharing sender. So you can configure.
So here you can find obtain an IP address automatically okay. So your system will allocate
IP automatically okay without your confirmation. So you don't need to allocate any IP okay.
So the system will automatically allocate that okay. So yesterday the MAC address was a0 and
the b0 the MAC address will not be changed the MAC address will be still the persistence.
So there is no changes in the MAC address. So if the police officer have a MAC address so
they can easily track who is the attacker who is the person or did that attack right.
So this why we need to track each and every packets instead of the network. So we are using
the MAC address for that. So we are using source MAC as well as the destination max. So
source MAC address will be your MAC address and the destination MAC address will be the Google
service or any other service you are using that MAC address okay. So finally we have a physical
layer. So we are knowing the physical layer. So we are converting this entire so data into
0 0 and 1 right 0 1 0 1 we are converting this into the bits right 0 1 0 1. So we need
to transfer this data through the cable right. So there is a fiber optics cable or any
electrical cable. So we need to transfer the data from here. So we need to transfer like
0 and 1 0 1 0 1 1 0 like that. So we are converting into the bits okay. So let us practically
see how our data will be into the machine. So I was using wires sharp for that. Let us leave
this and let us take our wire shock tool. I will explain few important things here. So I am
here and I am reaching to one of the domain called test well. So I am reaching to this web page and
I was signing up. So you can see it is not secured. It is in the HTTP format. So I am giving
the test and I am giving the username a test and password or something okay. So let us test
and test okay. I was giving the login. So now I can login into the so now I will go to
my wire shock and I will capture. So where shock is a pack and monitoring tool. It will monitor
each and every packet which was transferred from your machine to the other machine. Okay.
So I am not I just now I am stopping this and I was filtering that based on the HTTP. So
now you can see these are the recused because send from our place to the destination. So
now you can see my source IP will be this my IP address. So the source IP will be here and
the destination of 44.28 and I just gave it a it is a get recused. So you can find here
it is a test ppl.com. So this is the URL we have reached. So let us briefly understand.
So we discussed a lot of things in our OSM model. So you can see here right. So it is a
trans transmission control protocol. So you can see here the source port and the destination
port. So the destination thing was a HTTP protocol. So as per the HTTP the port number
the default port number will be the port 80. So we have a destination port port 80 and the error
control mechanism and sequence number everything will be added here. Right. So next sequence
number and everything will be here and the source port destination port and the transmission
control. So what's the protocols and everything will be everything will be here. Okay.
So next we discussed about the IP network layer. So this is the internet protocol IP address
I already said the IP address will be added. So you can see the source IP and the destination
IP of here in our packet and the next layer was a data link layer. So in the data link
layer. So this is my router MAC address and this is the source MAC on the destination
MAC will be added here and if you can see the bits, okay, 4,176 bits are there. Okay.
So now you can clearly find so how the OSM model help to understand the data communications
be previously discussed this in the network layer the IP address will be added in the transport
layer. So this based on the TCP. So we can find the transmission control protocol here.
So the TCP will be added in the Ethernet layer, the source MAC and the destination MAC has
been added and the frames 0s and 1s converting to 0s and 1s. Okay. So let's make it a simple
thing. So you here you can find so which request I have again given. So this is the URL
I have reached out and different Google from the Google I have reached out to the test
develop dot of PHP and here you can find the user agent so user agent will be the Chrome and
the windows. So this all the things are okay. Let's come to one of the interesting thing.
So we already discussed the encryption topic in the presentation layer, right in the presentation
layer in the encryption method. So the data will be encrypted into plain text to the
cipher text. Right. So let's go to the some logging pages. So now you can now now we can
find some something interesting. So this is a logging page we just given the username and
password. So let's track the data on by one. So now you can find here in this packet user
info dot PHP. So you can find I gave the test as a username and password as first week we
given a wrong password. So the wrong password T E R ST again we got a login page and again
we signed in. So now we gave the username as a test and password as a test. If there
is no encryption your data can be visible to everyone inside your network. This is a packet
capturing tool monitoring tool. We can monitor whatever packets which was sending which was
sending from the network. Okay. In the from the network, whatever packets was sending to the
modem or reaching out to the outside of the network, you can easily track that data and you
can monitor that data. So here you can easily find the username and password. Okay. So let's
go to an other logging page. So let's go to the.
Any other sign in and we will try to log in with our username and password. So I'm giving
the login register here. I'm giving something. So I'm doing the public name and the password
or something. I'm giving log in. So now this data will be also get. Sorry, it will not
be tracked because we have turned off that right. So let's play, play that one more time.
Okay. So I will continue without saving and I'm opening the, this time I will open
my incognito window and I will sign in to my Google. So something I was giving something
and a b c n gmail.com. And let's I will sign with my own account. Okay, we're sending something
to my phone. Let's ignore this and we'll go to another HTTP based page.
Okay. Let's log in into here. Let's, let's, no, it's too difficult to find some login
pages. Let's, I will check with my college. They have a username and password field to log
in. Let's use it using security for logging. Let's log in with the username and the password.
I was giving something. So now I will track this data in the virus total. Sorry, now we will
track this data in our workshop. So now we will filter it with the, uh, some get right
west. Oh, we reached to Samsung.
So basically it is like you can't able to find what you are sending. Okay, what you are logging
or what you are seeing, uh, the data will be untrackable. So what, what you are sending. That's
the power of encryption. So let's end this video and we will continue in the next video.
See you bye bye.